Guide to the Sociocultural Implications of High Technology Student Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Sociocultural Implications of High Technology student papers
1986-1990
SC0354
Stanford University
1.5 Linear feet
Collection consists of student papers produced through course work with series arrangement by academic quarter.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of student authors, 1986-1990.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Sociocultural Implications of High Technology, a writing-intensive course for graduates and undergraduates at Stanford University sponsored by Anthropology Professor Robert Textor, was created in 1986 to examine the consequences of high technology with the purpose of helping redress the balance between creating new technologies and assessing, anticipating, and understanding their social inpact.
Description of the Collection
Collection consists of student papers produced through course work with series arrangement by academic quarter.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of Anthropology.; Textor, Robert B.; Anthropology.; Science--History.; Technology and civilization.; Technology--Social aspects.
Collection Contents
- Student papers, 1986-1990
  - Crawford, Jennifer: Aids and the Sexual Revolution: Changes in the Homosexual and Heterosexual Cultures, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 12/18/86, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hemphill, Audrey: Biogenetic Engineering's Impact on the Family Farm. Genie or Jinx?, Anthro 238, 12/86, Deed of Gift, 1986 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Keeley, Sandra: How will Cultural Phenomena Impact Japan's Move Towards Innovation?, Anthro 238, 12/15/86, 1986 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Leung, Wyatt W.H.: The Evolution of Intelligent Writing Machines, Anthro 238/VISS 159, 12/16/86, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manning, Bart R.: Goals, Issues and Options in Radioactive Waste Disposal, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 12/16/86, 1986 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Osborne, Robert C.: The Sociocultural Implications of the Development of Neural-Based Computer Architecture, Anthro 138, 1986, Deed of Gift (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Osborne, Robert C.: Intelligent Machines: A New Direction for Computers and The Implications of Intelligent Machines, based upon previous paper entitled The Sociocultural Implications of the Development of Neural-Based Computer Architecture, Anthro 138, 1986, Deed of Gift (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Smith, Johanna: Genes and Joules: New Futures for Energy and Biotechnology, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 12/15/86, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Welsh, Justin: Electronic Communications in the Year 2012, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 12/15/86, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Blackwell, Cotton M.: Sweet Dreams and Sticky Business: NASA Sours Corporate American on Space, Anthro 138, 12/18/87, 1986 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bodman, Matthew: The Stanford Overseas Studies Program: Anticipatory visions, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 12/17/87, 1986 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brown, Kelly: The Nature of Computers and Their Role in Nuclear Defense: Command, Control and launch on Warning, Anthro 138, Revised January 1988, Deed of Gift, 1988 January (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chin, Ritchie J.: Telecommunications and the Information Age: Equity Issue Within the U.S., Anthro 238, 12/16/87, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Churchill, Stephen: High Technology and the American Presumption of Liberty, VTSS 159, 12/18/87, 1986 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Doub, Eric: High Technologies and the Well-Being of Women: Foundations for a Pessimistic Scenario on the Impacts of New Reproductive Technologies, Anthro 138, Fall 1987, Deed of Gift, 1987 Fall (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fernandez, Peter Martin: The Technological and Sociocultural Implications of Developing a Solar-Powered Electrical Utility in the Southwest U.S., Anthro 138, Autumn Quarter 1987-8, Deed of Gift, photo, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Goto, Kimie: Computers: Survival Games for US and Japan, VTSS 159, 12/15/87, 1986 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gwosdof, Adam S.: Text into Context: Theories of Autonomous Technology and Societal Phenomenon, VTSS 159, 12/15/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hardie, Edward: Disjunctive Technology and the Volt Weevil: A Cautionary Tale in an Alabama Voice, Anthro 237, 1987, (2 copies), Deed of Gift (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hecker, Janine: The New Reproductive Technologies, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hagg, Christopher: Biotechnology and Alternative Sociocultural Futures For The World, Anthro 138, Fall 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hess, Claudia: Pre-Adapted for Technology: Japan As a World Leader, Anthro 138, 12/16/87, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 16 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ho, William J.: Computer Aided Diagnosis and Therapy in Medicine, Anthro 138, 12/12/87, 1987 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hoffman, Brian: Bio-Tech, Development, and Peace: A strategy For Peace Between Jordan and Israel, Anthro 138/238, 12/15/87, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Johnson, Mia N.: Appropriate Technology and the Liberation of Japanese Women, 12/10/87, 1987 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kitcher, Scott: Japanese and American Economic Competition: A Japanese Model for Increased American Competitiveness, Anthro 138, 12/20/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kowalski, Roberta: Drugs in the Workplace, 3/18/88, 1988 March 18 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - McLaughlin, Susan: Die Gruen, Nuclear Weapons, and the United States, Anthro 138, 1/15/88, 1988 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - McTighe, Alice K.: Computers in Education: The Connection with Technical Literacy, VTSS 159, 12/18/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miccolis, Eduardo: Communication Satellites: The Political, Economical and Technical Interdependence, Anthro 138, 12/18/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Moffitt, Linda: Superconductors: The Race and the Impact, VTSS 159, 12/16/1987, 1987 December 16 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mohler, Thomas H.: Pinball Wizards, or How Can Non-Linear Information Systems Enhance Creativity?, VTSS 159, 12/15/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mohler, Thomas H.: Version 2 of Pinball wizards..., Deed of Gift (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pashigian, Melissa J.: Social Implications of In vitro Fertilization, Anthro 138, 3/3/88, Deed of Gift, 1988 March 3 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pastore, Mark: Technophobia and Technophilia: An Examination of the Intangible Implications of the Microelectronic Revolution, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 12/12/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ramirez, Martin F.: Recombinant DNA and the Second Green Revolution: A Study of the Implications of Genetic Engineering on Third World Agricultural Development, Anthro 138, 12/27/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 27 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rothstein, Nicole: Biological Weapons: Where We've Been and Where We are Heading, Anthro 238, 12/17/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rybkowski, Tenia: Microelectronics as a Mechanism for Change and Preservation in Saudi Society, Anthro 238, 12/20/87, Deed of Gift, 1987 December 20 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sturney, Kira E.: The Biogenetic Revolution: An Overview of the Implications and current Approach to Biogenetic Technology, VTSS 159, 12/18/86, Deed of Gift, 1986 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Thams, Kurt: Taming the Shrewd: Computer Networks and Human Values, photocopy of published version (Journal of Technology Studies), Deed of Gift (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Alexander, Jeffery M.: A Humane Approach to DeVelopment and Technology Theory: A Value-Driven Paradigm Based on the Sarvodya Shramadana Movement, 1988, Deed of Gift, photograph (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Anuzis, Adria: Characteristics of Japan's Technology Flows to Developing Countries, Anthro 238, 12/15/88, Deed of Gift, 1988 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Beardsley, Margery K.: Information Technology: Implications for Stanford, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bezmalinovic, Bea: Agriculture of Change: Non-Traditional Agricultural Exports, Technology and Costa Rican Social Democracy, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Freling, Dana Lynn: Anthropological Perspectives on Artificial Intelligence and Traditional Chinese Medicine in the People's Republic of China, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 11/8/88, Deed of Gift, 1988 November 8 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kassarjian, Raffi: Telecommunications and France: A New Social order, Anthro 138, 12/15/88, Deed of Gift, 1988 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Keare, stacy: A Study of Robotics in Japan, Anthro 138, 12/15/88, Deed of Gift, 1988 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Kiesel, Patrica L.: Microelectronics, Information and Soviet Society, Anthro 138, 12/15/88, Deed of Gift, 1988 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Shein, Jean-Emmnanuel.: The Social Products of High Technology, Culture Industry, Mass Consumption and Youth: An Anthropological Analysis of the Japanese case, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Toyoda, A. Maria: Magnetic Resonance Imaging: Not Everything is Crystal-Clear, VTSS 159, 12/15/88, Deed of Gift: A case for Treatment: Magnetic Resonance Imaging as an Example of High Technology and the Health care Market, honors thesis, Spring 1989, 1988 December 15 and 1989 Spring (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Winden, Andrew: A "Comedy of Errors": Japan's Role As a Source of Technology Transfer to Developing Countries, Anthro 238/VTSS 159, 12/15/88, Deed of Gift, 1988 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Barnard, Paul: Possible American Responses to Pressures from Japanese Technological Success, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Kettell, Cheryl: Acquired Immune Deficiency syndrome and Its Impact on the American Indian Community, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miller, Michelle: The Effect of New Technologies on the Field of Archaeology, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Wasow, Omar Thomas: Projected Sociocultural Effects of Interactive Video Technology on American Society and Education, 1989, Deed of Gift (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Kozel, Scott: Really Solving our Energy Problems: An Irreverent Proposal, VTSS 259, 6/12/89, 1989 June 12 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Patterson, Kate: Disposable Consumer Plastics and Opportunities for Ethical Decision-Making, Anthro 268, Spring 1989, Deed of Gift, 1989 Spring (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Bunch, Charles: Computers in Composition Instruction: An Insider's View of Sociocultural Developments, VTSS 159, 5/14/90, Deed of Gift, 1990 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Fuselier, Christopher W.: Educational Futures and the American Underclass: Computers, Culture, and Equal Opportunity, VTSS 159, 3/22/90, Deed of Gift, 1990 March 22 (Box 3, Folder 19)